Guide to the Oral History of the American Left: Radical Histories Collection OH 002
Tamiment Library / Wagner Archives
- O
  - Name: O'Connor, Harvey Description: Activities in Seattle around time of 1919 general strike; work in the Federated Press, 1920s-40s; relationships with Communists, also old-time labor editors and ethnic radicals such as Ludwig Lore; activities in Pittsburgh, 1930s; attack by House Un-American Activities Committee, 1950s., Sep 27, 1977 (Box 2)
  - Name: Ocko, Edna Description: Left and dance in the 1930s-40s; form and content in radicalism and modern dance., 1981 (Box 2)
  - Name: Ollman, Bertell Description: Background in Milwaukee, 1940s-50s; radicalism in Madison; political activities and intellectual growth in Madison Students League for Industrial Democracy, Students for Democratic Action, and others organizations; reflections on Madison experience., Nov 5, 1982 (Box 2)
- P-Q
  - Name: Page, Myra Description: Southern writer and novelist; family background and childhood in Norfolk, Va,; circumstances of her writing The Gathering Storm and Moscow Yankee, 1930s., 1982 (Box 2)
    tape#: 2 U2Q
  - Name: Pandera, John Description: Left in South Slav sections of San Pedro 1930s-1950s, Oct 22, 1982 (Box 2)
    tape#: 1 U2Q
  - Name: Patterson, Louise Thompson Description: Youth in Sacramento CA; her move to NYC; harlem in 1920s-1930s; Scottsboro case in 1930s., Nov 16, 1981-Nov 30, 1981 (Box 2)
    tape#: 5 U2Q
  - Name: Perocco, Albert Description: Bridgeport (Connecticut) Socialist Party, 1960s, its prospects after the end of the long tenure of Jasper McLevy as Socialist Mayor of Bridgeport., Jan 19, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Name: Perry, Elaine Description: Women's role in WWII electrical industry in New Jersey; National Negro Congress; UE vs IUE; reflections., Mar 26, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Name: Peters, Irja M. Description: Growing up in Finnish-American left of the 1930s in Mesabi Range; unhappy marriage to non-Finnish intellectual; return to roots., Jul 30, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Name: Pevzner, Sam Description: Pennsylvania IWO; background as Jewish entertainer, and political conversion; activities within sphere of the Yiddishe Kultur Farband., Jun 26, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Name: Phillips, Utah Description: IWW folk singer recalling experiences from 1940s to present, on WBJC (Baltimore) radio broadcast., undated (Box 2)
  - Name: Podmaka, Rose Description: Background in coal and steel region of Ohio-West Virginia, 1930s; United Electrical Workers-Hatfield Wire and Cable, New Jersey, 1940s; UE and the Association of Catholic Trade Unionists., Jan 22, 1979-Mar 19, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Name: Pollier, Justine Description: Recollections of legal work, 1930s; origins of National Lawyers' Guild., Jun 22, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Name: Popular Front Culture Description: Discussion led by Paul Buhle, includes A.B. Magil, Steve Max, Steve Nelson, Nat Cohen and others, about the meaning of "culture" to younger generation in the Popular Front; attitudes toward sports, particularly baseball in Left and in the Daily Worker; neighborhood activity around cultural themes in New York., Dec 3, 1977 (Box 2)
    tape#: 3 U2R
  - Name: Porterfield, Pearl Zeluck Description: Johnson-Forest Tendency, Workers Party 1940s, May 7, 1983 (Box 2)
    tape#: 1 U2R
  - Name: Prago, Albert Description: Lectures by Albert Prago, John Gerassi, Carl Marzani, Dante Puzzo, David Rabinowitz, Murray Solow, Carl Geiser; songs of the Spanish Civil War by Pete Seeger., Oct 20, 1981-Dec 8, 1981 (Box 2)
    tape#: 13 U2R
  - Name: Puropudas, Timo Description: Finnish background; role as editor of Tyomies since 1970s; technical problems and outlook; attitudes towards status and future of ethnic press; life as recent immigrant. Editor of Tyomies since 1970s, Finnish, Jul 31, 1983 (Box 2)
    tape#: 2 U2R
  - Name: Preston, William Description: University of Wisconsin, early 1950s; impact of William Appleman Williams and others on historical studies; Madison social and political milieu; his research on the Indus- trial Workers of the World; experiences as a historian., Aug 10, 1983 (Box 2)
- R
  - Name: Rasmussen, Paul Andreas Description: Political background in Illinois Socialist Party and Workers Alliance, late 1920s/early 1930s; activities within Socialist Party and formation of Socialist Workers Party; expulsion from Socialist Workers Party, 1947., Apr 3, 1984, 1972 (Box 2)
    tape#: 20 U2S
  - Name: Rawick, George Description: Family background; adolescence in Brooklyn; experience around YCL and Wallace movement, late 1940s; expulsion and attraction to Shachtmanite movement; activities, 1950s; influence of Shachtmanites on New Left.t, Oct 4, 1984 (Box 2)
    tape#: 2
  - Name: Raymond, Philip Description: Auto Workers Union, 1920s-early 1930s; political scene in Detroit; ethnic communities of auto workers., Oct 22, 1982 (Box 2)
    tape#: 2 U2T
  - Name: Raynes, Rose Description: Emma Larazus Federation, International Workers Order, 1930s., Mar 21, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Name: Ribak, George and Al Description: Bridgeport (Connecticut) Socialist Party, 1910s-1940s; recollections of two long-time former Socialist Party activists., Apr 1, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Name: Richards, Harvey Description: Labor activity in the 1930s-1950s; radical film-making from early 1960s; early work with SNCC and use of film as educational/ fundraising tool; making films about destruction of Redwood trees and Bay Area Vietnam protest movement., Nov 5, 1983 (Box 2)
    No transcript or index available
    tape#: 1 U2T
  - Name: Richards, Paul Description: Bay Area background; multi-racial, working class Left of Oakland, Cal. contrasted with middle class, largely white community Madison, Wisconsin; activities as an open Communist in Madison, late 1960s; departure from Communist Party; observations about student Left; reflections on life since., Nov 5, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Name: Rivkin, Minnie Description: Russian background; Yiddish Chorus, 1930-present; generation gap and Yiddishkayt., Apr 7, 1980 (Box 2)
    tape#: 4 U2T
  - Name: Rodney, Lester Description: Family background in Bensonhurst, Brooklyn; origins of his radicalism and interest in sports; sportswriting for the Daily Worker, from 1930s; on Joe Louis, Cardinals' strike, other events; effects of Cold War period., Dec 29, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Name: Ronch, I.A. Description: Political cultural life in Allerton Avenue Coops, Bronx, 1920s-1950s; cultural life inside Yiddish-speaking sector of Communist Party; role as leader of Jewish People's Chorus, 1950s; cultural/poetic activities in Los Angeles, 1960s-1970s., Apr 14, 1981 (Box 2)
    tape#: 6 U2T U2U
  - Name: Rosenberg, Nina Description: Yiddish cultural movement, Miami Beach, since 1940s., Mar 14, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Name: Rosenberg, Sadie Description: Youth and family life, 1920s; International Workers Order, Trade Union Unity League, Young Communist League, Brooklyn, 1930s-40s; United Electrical Workers Local 427- Solar Manufacturing Co., Bayonne, N.J., 1940s., Jan 11, 1979-Jan 15, 1979 (Box 2)
    tape#: 3 U2T
  - Name: Rosencrantz, Paul Description: Communist Party, National Maritime Union, factory organizing in New York and in Maine., Jan 15, 1981 (Box 2)
    tape#: 2 U2V
  - Name: Rossi, Florence Description: Hunter College Socialist Party, early 1930s; Socialist Party, 1930s., Mar 17, 1982 (Box 2)
    tape#: 1 U2V
  - Name: Rubel, Dan Description: Jefferson School of Social Science; impact of the Cold War., Apr 12, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Name: Rubinstein, Annette Description: Joining the Communist Party; American Labor Party activities; Mike Quill; Jefferson School; leaving CP; life and activities since 1950s., 1981 (Box 2)
  - Name: Rubinstein, Annette Description: Long Island background; political and union People's Molilization, American Labor Party; day care and birth control information campaigning; School for Democracy and Jefferson School, 1940s-1950s; effects of McCarthyism., Dec 18, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Name: Rudiak, Joe Description: Life in small industrial town, Pennsylvania, 1920s-30s; union activities and Left affiliation; electoral campaign and red-baiting, 1930s; life in Pittsburgh and work in fraternal societies., Jun 28, 1983 (Box 2)
    tape#: 4 U2V
  - Name: Rudiak, Joe & Muselin, Peter & Luketich, Bernard Description: Nature and activity of the Croatian Fraternal Union; changes since 1920s; emergence of "progressive" leadership, 1940s-50s; and service to the membership; present activities, insurance and cultural., Jun 8, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Name: Ruuttila, Julia Description: Industrial Workers of the World, Oregon and Washington, 1910s., Sep 7, 1972 (Box 2)
- S
  - Name: Santora, William Description: Early life in Jersey City, work at Emerson Radio N.Y., United Electrical Workers staff member helped organize Fed. Tel. and Tel., Westinghouse Elevator Co., N.J., influence of the left., Jul 24, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Name: Saroff, Sophie Description: Family background in Russia, 1905 Revolution; Rand School, ILGWU and Camp Unity; 1930s International Labor Defense., Dec 14, 1979 (Box 2)
    tape#: 5 U2V
  - Name: Saroff, Sophie Description: Recording of 80th b-day party, May 15, 1979 (Box 2)
    tape#: 2 U2W
  - Name: Schirmer, Daniel Boone Description: National Students' League, CIO & students, Mar 18, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Name: Schwartz, Charles Description: Background in Fall River, 1950s-1960s; high school radicalization on; life and politics in Madison, late 1960s; down and out in California; return to New England, activities in Left, 1970s-1980s., Apr 21, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Name: Schwartz, Chaym Description: Activity as Yiddish poet in Yiddish Cultural circles, 1930s-present., Dec 29, 1981 (Box 2)
    tape#: 1 U2W
  - Name: Seeger, Pete Description: Use of music as social protest; growing up in 1930s with folk music; Communist Party song book; war and prison sentence; sense of humor and curiosity; songs on Scottosboro and International Labor Defense., Feb 25, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Name: Segal, Berl Description: Workman' Circle, Providence, R.I., 1920s-40s; ethnic socialist groups in Providence; Socialists and Communists., May 4, 1977 (Box 2)
    Indexavailable
  - Name: Segal, Edith Description: Music and dance and the Left in the 1930s., Feb 7, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Name: Seid, Irving Description: New York background; Depression and Unemployed Councils; McCarthyism., Jun 4, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Name: Seid Tauhma Description: Youth in Yorkville section of New York, 1920s; cafeteria workers unionism; Young Communist League; Communist Party, 1940s-50s., Jun 4, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Name: Seidlitz, Leo Description: Brooklyn College radical politics, mid-1930s; Trotskyism, late 1930s; Workers Party, 1940s, and later influence of Max Shachtman., Jul 20, 1983 (Box 2)
    tape#: 3 U2W
  - Name: Serrano, Nina Description: Bohemian observations of middle-American Madison in 1950s; recruitment into Youth Labor League; activities in founding of the Peace Center; travel to Peace Festival, Moscow and to China; subsequent difficulty in school, Madison; maintaining contact with former Madison friends., Nov 16, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Name: Sharron, Mark Description: Workers Party, Trotskyism, Workers' Party, Max Shachtman, 1930s-1950s., May 5, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Name: Sharron, Mark Description: Russian background; Brownsville childhood; City College of New York and Young Communist League; Trotskyism; European experiences; Workers Party and World War II., Aug 19, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Name: Sharron, Mark Description: Activity in the Trotskyist movement of the 1930s-40s; Trotskyism and international questions; character of the Workers Party., Nov 10, 1983 (Box 2)
    tape#: 2 U2X
  - Name: Shenton, John Description: Socialist Party, Bridgeport, Conn., 1920-60., Jun 20, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Name: Shore, Anne Description: Communist Party; United office and Professional Workers of America (UOPWA); picketing of the Nazi ship Bremen; Detroit, 1940s; Civil Rights Congress and Progressive Party, Los Angeles, late 1940s-early 1950s; effects of McCarthy period; work for 1199 (Hospital Workers), 1960s., May 31, 1982-Jun 15, 1982 (Box 2)
    tape#: 8 U2X
  - Name: Silverstein, Robert J. & Meyers, Howard Description: International Labor Defense, National Lawyers Guild 1930s-40s, Jun 22, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Name: Simon, S. Fanny Description: Socialist Party 1930s, Feb 12, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Name: Smith, Jessie Taft Description: Family background in Norwalk, Connecticut, 1910s-1920s; Young Communist League, laundry workers' union, social and political life, 1930s., Nov 19, 1981 (Box 2)
    tape#: 2 U2Y
  - Name: Soble, Richard Description: Radical legal work in Detroit, 1960s-70s, including "Red Squad" lawsuit, late 1960s rent strike., Mar 31, 1983 (Box 2)
    tape#: 1 U2Y
  - Name: Socialist Labor Party Description: Socialist Labor Party "South Slavonian" language federation, 1920s-50s, Detroit and Cleveland., Mar 17, 1983 (Box 2)
    tape#: 4 U2Y
  - Name: Southern Negro Youth Congress Description: Forum on its history, with one-time SNYC activists Henry Winston, James Jackson, Grace Tillman Bassett, Esther Jackson, and Dorothy Burnham., Feb 6, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Name: Spok, Anton Description: Activities in Milwaukee Croatian Fraternal Union, 1930s-present; labor activities in Milwaukee during 1930s; theatrical activities of interviewee, a prominent amateur Croatian-American actor in Milwaukee., Jul 26, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Name: Stern, Sholem Description: Radical Yiddish writer and poet, Montreal and New York, 1920s-30s., Sep 18, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Name: Steuzert, Isidor Description: The Jewish Socialist Federation, American Communism, the Lovestoneites., Oct 27, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Name: Suller, Chaim Description: Background in Jewish progressive movement; problems of the Morgen Freiheit today., Jan 20, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Name: Swabeck, Arne Description: Scandinavian Socialist Federation and press, Oct 23, 1982 (Box 2)
    tape#: 49 U2Z U2AA U2BB
  - Name: Swabeck, Arne Description: Large collections of interviews taken in the 1970s, Apr 7, 1975-Apr 11, 1975 (Box 2)
  - Name: Syrstad, A.O. Description: Workers Party, Independent Socialist League, Seattle, Washington, 1940s-1950s., Jan 5, 1978 (Box 2)
    tape#: 1 U2BB
- T
  - Name: Taffler, Anna Description: Unemployed Council Brooklyn 1930-1934, Jan 5, 1978 (Box 2)
    tape#: 2 U2BB
  - Name: Thomas, Norman Description: Reminiscences, 1960 (Box 2)
  - Name: Thomas, Norman Description: Recollections of Jasper McLevy, Socialist Mayor of Bridgeport, Conn., 1933-1957., Nov 17, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Name: Norman Thomas 1932 Campaign, 50th anniversary Description: Various speakers including Ruth Senior, Mickey Most, Herb Wolfe, John Herling, Noah Walter, Michael Harrington; recollections of Thomas' first presidential campaign and his overall career and influence., Nov 19, 1982-Nov 20, 1982 (Box 2)
    tape#: 6 U2CC
  - Name: Thomashow, Bessie Description: Workmen's Circle, 1930s, undated (Box 2)
    tape#: 1 U2CC
  - Name: Thompson, Fred Description: Nature of language federations attached to Industrial Workers of the World; prominent immigrant figures in IWW; eclipse of language federations and ethnic press in IWW., Jul 26, 1983 (Box 2)
    tape#: 2 U2CC
  - Name: Thorne, Ahrne Description: Polish background; education of an anar- chist; Yiddish anarchism in the US since the 1920s; Yiddish anarchism and Zionism; Rudolf Rocker., Jan 22, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Name: Travaglio, Esther Hartz Description: Activity of "Gene" Travaglio, anarchist activist and job-printer in Seattle and in California; background and activities of Esther Hartz Travaglio., Oct 30, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Name: Tuuomien, Uhro Description: Activity of "younger" generation of Finnish-American radicals, in midwest and California; tenacity and decline of Finnish- American activity in Bay Area; effort of Communist and non-Communist Finnish-Americans to engage in common functions., Nov 5, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Name: Tussey, Jean Description: Steel Workers Organizing Committee, Sociallist Party, and Socialist Workers Party in New Jersey and Southern California, 1930s-early 1940s., Oct 24, 1978-Oct 25, 1978, Mar 20, 1979 (Box 2)
    tape#: 3 U2CC
- U
  - Name: Unemployed Organizations of the 1930s Description: Session of 1983 New York State Labor History Association meeting. Presentation by Roy Rosenzweig, followed by panel discussion with Saul Parker, John Gates, Rose Schuyler, Brendan Sexton., Apr 30, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Name: Uphaus, Willard and Ruth MacLennan Description: Life of Willard and Ruth with special emphasis on 1930s; background of the two; their meeting in 1930s, religion-political activity, friendship with Claude Williams, activity for Socialism., Jul 20, 1983 (Box 2)
    tape#: 2 U2DD
- V
  - Name: Vidali, Vittorio Description: Italian Language Federation, American Communist movement, 1920s; Chicago and the Left; reflections on American Communism; translated from his autobiography., Aug 6, 1981 (Box 2)
  - Name: Vishnu, Abraham & Becker, Getzel Description: Immigrant experiences, radicalism and culture in New York and Miami Beach; anti-semitism in radical movements of Poland; life for Jewish workers in pre-revolutionary Cuba; importance of Yiddish culture for political movements, 1920s-1950s., Oct 25, 1978 (Box 2)
- W
  - Name: Wallin, Frank Description: Editorial activities for Tyomies and Industrilistii, Finnish-American IWW newspaper; life of a Finnish-American radical newspaperman, 1940s-1970s., Jul 31, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Name: Warren Susan Description: Committee for a Democratic Far Eastern Policy; Jefferson School of Social Science, 1950s., Apr 17, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Name: Waskow, Arthur Description: Students for a Democratic Society, Apr 2, 1970 (Box 2)
    tape#: 1
  - Name: Weir, Stan Description: C.L.R. James and Johnson-Forest Tendency, Workers Party, Oct 22, 1982 (Box 2)
    tape#: 2 U2EE
  - Name: Weiss, Myra Tanner Description: Family and educational background in Salt Lake City and Los Angeles; unemployed movement and Trotskyist movement, 1930s-1940s; anti-fascist demonstrations; experiences as Socialist Workers Party candidate, 1940s-1950s., 1982 (Box 2)
    tape#: 1 U2EE
  - Name: Weiss, Sam Description: Role of the Freie Arbeter Shtimme (Free Voice of Labor) in the labor movement of the 1920s-1930s; role of anarchists within Arbeter Ring, New York and Los Angeles., Apr 8, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Name: Wellman, Saul Description: Communists & United Auto Workers during WWII, Hitler-Stalin pact, cold war and Left, Aug 24, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Name: Wellman, Saul Description: 65th birthday dinner, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Name: Wiese, Ed Description: Westinghouse Elevator Plant, Jersey City, influence of left; Pres. Local 456; U.E., 1981 (Box 2)
  - Name: West, Yvette Description: Background in father's house; conflicts with stepmother; youth in IWW, mid-1930s; father (Yiddish critic B. Rivkin), his literary career and her relationship with him., Jan 19, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Name: Williams, Jim Description: Students for a Democratic society 1960s, Apr 2, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Name: Williams, Paul W. Description: Prosecution of International Workers' Order 1950s, May 11, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Name: Wohlforth, Tim Description: Background in Bridgeport, Connecticut, 1930s-40s; Socialism and Trotskyism, 1950s., Aug 29, 1976 (Box 2)
  - Name: Wolfson, Alice Dodge Description: League for Industrial Democracy, Office Workers Union, New England CIO and Socialist Party, 1930s., Apr 1, 1982 (Box 2)
    tape#: 1 U2FF
  - Name: Workers Party/Standing Fast Conference Description: Commemorating the opening of the Max Shachtman Papers at the Tamiment Library; panel presentations on 1) the character and activities of the Workers Party, 1940-49 2) Harvey Swados' novel Standing Fast, based on the WP, and 3) three magazines with roots in the WP, Politics, Dissent, and New Politics. Speakers include Herman Benson, Ricky Flanders, Albert Glotzer, Julius Jacobson, Irving Sanes, Morton Clurman, Paul Cowan, Lewis Coser, Robert Cummings, Phyllis Jacobson., May 6, 1983-May 7, 1983 (Box 2)
    tape#: 5 U2FF
  - Name: Wright, Frederick Description: Background of family, grandfather's influence on Fred's drawing; work as a clip- joint musician, 1920s; shipping out, 1930s; cartooning for NMU as freelancer; Cold War and shift to UE News; evolution and reflections., Jun 20, 1984 (Box 2)
- X-Y-Z
  - Name: Yellin, Fanny Description: Anarchist circle in Philadelphia, 1910s; personality and ideas of Rudolf Rocker; role of the Rocker Circle, Los Angeles, in publishing Rocker's work and facilitating his speaking tours., Apr 16, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Name: Yoneda, Karl Description: Japanese-American Communist movement in the 1920s-30s; Japanese-language press, 1920s and early 1930s; sectarian errors; cultural events; role in labor movement and opposition to internment camps; Popular Front in Japanese-American Left; Asian-American labor today., Jan 7, 1983 (Box 2)
  - Name: Young, Vincent Description: Youth in New York, 1920s-30s; involvement in black masonic lodge, Congress of Radical Equality, Brooklyn, 1940s-60s; Downstate Medical Center, New York World's Fair demonstrations; CORE conventions and campaigns., Aug 4, 1983 (Box 2)
    tape#: 3 U2FF
  - Name: Zackheim, Meyer Description: Recollections of New York Left in 1910s-20s; problems of Jewish progressive movement in Miami Beach, 1970s., Oct 24, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Name: Zackheim, Meyer & Kleiger, Ben Description: New York Progressive Yiddish activity in 1920s-40s; immigration and trade union experiences; role of progressive movement in Miami Beach Jewish community, 1970s., Oct 24, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Name: Zackheim, Meyer, Rothenberg, Archie, & Lipshitz, Rose Description: Problems of immigrant women (Rose Lipshitz) in America of 1920s and appeal of the Left; problems of the shop and appeal of cultural movement; political activities of Jewish Left in 1920s-30s (Rothenberg); YKUF reading circles today., Oct 24, 1978 (Box 2)
  - Name: Zawadowski, Joseph Description: Polish-American Left in Chicago from time of his father (1920s) to present; Spanish Civil War experiences; current activities of Chicago Left., Jul 28, 1983 (Box 2)
    tape#: 2 U2FF
  - Name: Zeluck, Steve Description: Johnson-Forest Tendency, 1940s; Trotskyist movement, Philadephia and Chicago; reflections on C.L.R. James., Dec 15, 1982 (Box 2)
  - Name: Zimmerman, Charles Description: International Ladies' Garment Workers Union, struggle between left and right, 1910s-1920s., Oct 31, 1974 (Box 2)
  - Name: Zitron, Celia Lewis Description: New York Teachers Union, 1940s, May 8, 1976 (Box 2)